one question for you have you been
profitable over the past 30 days if you
answered no let me show you a wildly
effective chart pattern that would have
made you profitable and before the
keyboard Warriors go at it in the
comments section this chart pattern has
not only been profitable over the past
30 days it's a chart pattern that I've
used to pull profits out of the market
for over eight years it's the same chart
pattern I used to get in the trade you
currently see on your screen and when
combined with the right technical
factors into a strategy it is a chart
pattern that can provide an insane Edge
over the market so in today's video
you're going to learn the number one
mistake keeping you from being
profitable and the chart pattern trading
strategy that can fix that issue so if
that sounds good go a and click that
like button for me go and subscribe if
you are new and I'll see you after the
intro and
[Music]
display welcome back and I want to Di
right into this chart pattern so we're
going to talk about the number one
mistake keeping you from being
profitable a little later in the video
but for now let's get started with the
chart pattern that would have made you
profitable over the last 30 days the
pattern I am referring to is double tops
and double bottoms but not traded in the
way you've heard about before in order
to get the insane results that you can
achieve with these patterns you have to
trade them in a very specific way and
with very specific rules and I'm going
to tell you those rules a little later
in the video but for now I want make
sure we cover the basics for anyone that
is brand new starting with what is a
double top and what is a double bottom
we're actually going to start with
double bottom so on the screen you can
see price pushing down and this is a
double bottom so when we have price
pushing down creating a pullback then
retesting the lowest low that price made
before the pullback and then seeing
price go higher and the opposite is true
for a double top that's when we see
price push up then we see a pullback
then we see a retest test of that
previous highest high followed by a
rejection that would be a double top now
how do we use these patterns in our
trading again we're going to have really
specific rules for them that actually
cause them to be profitable but let's go
ahead and go through the easy version of
how we use them now so these patterns
indicate possible reversals if price is
pushing lower and we see something like
this double bottom here that could be an
indication that prices are heading
higher and the opposite is true as well
if we see price pushing higher and we
see this double top form here that can
be an indication that prices are about
to fall or reverse now I'm going to go
over the very specific rules that cause
these patterns to be profitable and
after I do that I'm going to be sharing
with you what would have happened if you
would have traded this way for the past
30 days 90 days and for all of 2023 and
after that I'm going to be showing you
two trades that I'm in live right now
using exactly what you're learning in
this video so you can see that this
isn't completely in hindsight I actually
took a lot of the trades I'm going to be
sharing with you and again I have two
open trades there live right now using
this exact same chart pattern so let's
go ahead and dive into the rules we're
going to start off with a double bottom
this is the scenario I want to see first
for the rules for a double Bottom I want
to see price pushing lower I then want
to see the beginning stage of a pullback
or the start of a pullback when I see
the start of this pullback and then this
pullback begin to fail this is what that
looks like when that pullback begins to
fail we have our impulsive move down
right here we then have a pullback and
this when price starts to push lower
after the pullback would be the pullback
beginning to fail when that happens I'm
going to go ahead and create a
termination zone right back here and
this is what I mean by that when this
begins when we have the push down the
pullback the pullback beginning to fail
at that point I'm going to point out an
area between
the body and the low of this previous
swing low so the way that would look I
actually do it with a box tool I grab a
box tool I start at the body of those
candles I go all the way down to the low
that was created there the lowest point
of this first swing low and this is what
I call the termination Zone what this
means is that in order to have a valid
double bottom I need price to come down
and at least touch this Zone I can also
have price push down and close inside of
this Zone I can even see a wig go past
this Zone all of that would be a valid
double bottom I would have everything I
need to say I have a double bottom here
if any of those situations happened if
price came all the way down and closed
below maone at this point this would not
be a double bottom because if we get a
close below the lowest point of this
previous swing low that indicates that
we are likely to see Trend continuation
to the downside so the only scenarios
where I can see a valid trade are a
touch of determination Zone a close in
the termination Zone even a wick going
beyond the termination zone is fine but
a candle closing beyond the termination
Zone would invalidate this as a double
bottom let's go ahead and see what price
does so I can explain this further as
you can see price plays around a bit but
eventually do we get a touch of our
termination
Zone the answer is yes right here prices
now touch the termination zone so these
are my conditions for a double bottom if
price would have closed down here inside
of this termination Zone would I have a
valid double bottom yes I would if we
had a wick that went past it would this
be a valid double bottom yes it would if
this candle came all the way down and
closed outside of the Zone I created
from the lowest Wick to the lowest body
of this first swing low would that be
valid no that's the only thing that
would invalidate this as a double bottom
so so now we have the objective rules
that can keep us consistent and these
are the rules that I found to be most
profitable when it comes to spotting
double bottoms and we'll go over double
tops in a second but here's how we spot
the pattern we can't just trade based on
spotting the pattern though after we
create the conditions for whatever
pattern we're trading we need a specific
reason why we enter every time we see
this setup occur so at this point we
have our setup I'm going to go aad and
break down the entry stops and targets
as well if you're unfamiliar this is an
acronym I call
CEST and it's the acronym I use to
create or trade any strategy that I ever
create or trade it stands for conditions
which are what we just discussed the
conditions of this double bottom an
entry reason stops and targets I would
highly recommend that you create an
acronym for yourself or use this one
anytime you're placing a trade so at
this point we have the conditions met
for an entry what I have seen to work
best with this pattern pattern and in
this specific way of trading is placing
an entry right at the high of what we
call the neckline of this double bottom
this double bottom consists of a bottom
a neckline which is the highest point of
the pullback before the push back lower
and at this point the highest point of
that neckline is where I enter the
market now you have a couple of choices
on this you can either wait around and
just watch price to see when it actually
touches this zone for me I use what's
called a bu stop order which means I'm
telling my broker I want to get involved
in this trade when price or if price
pushes high enough to hit my order my
buy stop order would be right here again
at the top of this neckline so this
trade would look something like having a
buy stop order right there at my blue
line for a stop loss I'm going to go one
pip below the lowest low of our double
bottom whether it's this low the initial
one or if this low would have been lower
my stop loss would just go below that
low so it depends on which low is lowest
but that's where my stop loss is going
to go after that I normally manage the
position but for the sake of this video
being more simplistic we're going to go
with a 1.4 to1 reward to risk ratio on
all these trades and so remember we're
not even going to be involved in this
trade unless we hit this blue line at
this point we have all the conditions
met for a double bottom but we don't
have the entry criteria met yet because
the entry criteria after we see all of
this other stuff occur is that we need
price to push high enough to break this
neckline which is where my order would
be sitting in this specific scenario
let's go ahe and click
play as you can see we've now been
entered into the trade price then
continues to climb and eventually climbs
high enough to hit that 1.4 to1 Target
so a quick recap of a double bottom
before we move on to double tops we are
going to wait for this first initial
swing low to occur we're going to wait
for a pullback that then begins to fail
by pushing back lower we're going to
create a termination Zone zone between
the body and the low of that initial low
of the double bottom then we're going to
wait and see if price eventually comes
down and at least touches this area can
close inside of it can Wick past it
cannot close below it as long as that
occurs we have a valid double Bottom
already but we're not entering the trade
just because of that valid double bottom
criteria our entry criteria or at least
for me the way I've traded this and seen
it to be most profitable is having that
entry criteria be when price crosses
above the neckline of our double bottom
that will be the entry in for stops and
targets super simple stops just below
the lowest point of the double bottom
targets at this point at a 1.4 to one
reward to risk ratio now for a double
top we'll speed it up a bit here because
it should be pretty easy to comprehend
since you just learned about that double
bottom and this is literally just the
opposite we have price pushing higher
what we're waiting on is to see price
push higher create a p pullback and then
that pullback begin to fail in an
uptrend that would look like this as
soon as that pullback begins to fail and
sellers are no longer in control that's
when we want to start looking for a
possible double top at the point that
the pullback begins to fail as in we
start to get a little bit of a push
higher I'm going to create that same
termination Zone except this time it's
going to be between the bodies and the
highest point of that initial swing high
that we started with before the pullback
and failure to continue pushing lower at
this point what do you think we're
looking for well the opposite is true as
to what we had with the double bottom we
want to see price at least touch our
termination Zone we can see price come
up here and close inside of our
termination Zone we can even see a wick
go past the termination Zone what we do
not want to see is price come up here
and close all the way above that
termination Zone that would be an
invalid double top because if we had a
close above o this High then chances are
we're looking at Trend continuation not
a double top and possible reversal so in
that case and with that let's go ahead
and push the market forward as you can
see we're inside of our zone now and
after we touch the Zone what's the next
step well same criteria for entry right
here we're going to be looking at the
neckline of this double top we had price
push higher we have that push down the
failure to continue pushing down that is
going to be our neckline the lowest
point of that for this double top
scenario and this for me at least is
where I would be putting a sell stop
order with a stop loss right above the
swing high of this pattern whichever
high is higher again if this second high
was a little bit higher my stop loss
would just go right above it but instead
right here is where that stop loss is
going to go with that being the case I'm
going to put a 1.4 to1 reward to risk
ratio for these examples and I can go
ahead and click play now and as you can
see after hitting play this is a trade
that did in fact come down down far
enough to hit our targets and this is a
trade I actually took earlier in the
week now let's take a look at the
results you would have had if you would
have traded exactly what you just
learned throughout the past 30 days and
throughout all of 2023 and stick around
after that because I'll be showing you
two other technical factors you can add
to this chart pattern to make it go from
profitable to extremely profitable to
make it go from accurate to extremely
accurate but for now let's take a look
at the results you would have had if you
would have traded this for the last 30
days what you can see right now is the
chart of the euro dollar the red lines
are going to be losses and the green
lines are obviously going to be wins we
had a 1.4 reward to risk ratio just as I
showed you earlier in this video for
each of these trades and as you can see
throughout the last 30 days on the euro
dollar you would have had three losses
and five wins and what that means is
that you would have made an 8% Roi now I
know there might be some of you out
there that think 8 8% a month is low
it's not 8% is a great return if you can
make it consistently every single month
but also I want you to keep in mind this
is on one currency pair obviously we're
not just going to be trading a single
currency pair so imagine having not just
one of these but multiple let's say you
find three pairs that perform in a
similar way at that point you would be
looking at more like a 24% month not
that you would get 24% every single
month I just want you to have an idea of
what's possible when you use a trading
strategy that has a positive expectancy
and you battle through draw Downs even
though you have some losses and continue
trading it these are the kind of results
that you could possibly get now what
about throughout all of 2023 we don't
want to just see the results for the
last 30 days we want to see results over
a long period of time so throughout all
of 2023 these were the results I'll go
ahe and scroll back so you can see my
testing again red lines are losses green
lines are wins feel free to test this
yourself which I do recommend this this
goes all the way back to the start of
2023 and throughout that time we got 26
wins and 17 losses so we'll bring up a
calculator yet again we have 26 wins all
of those we're at a 1.4 to1 reward risk
ratio we had 17 losses so we now
subtract those 17 losses because they're
equal to one and then we get 19.4 what
we call R 19.4 R means 19.4 times
whatever we're risking I personally risk
2% you may risk more or less but that
would give a
38.8% Roi throughout 2023 and again keep
in mind that's just trading it on one
pair if you had let's say three pairs
that were performing in a similar way
and you traded them all year that would
be more than a 100% gain this year with
just this strategy alone now I'm going
to be teaching you two other technical
factors that can take this already good
chart pattern and turn it into a great
trading strategy so as you can see on
the screen this is actually the trade
from the intro we've had quite a
pullback since the intro of this video
but I've moved my stop loss up to a 1.4
to1 reward to risk ratio meaning that's
my worst case scenarios I hit a 1.4 or
around $4,700 currently we're at $7,100
I'm really hoping we can see this thing
take off to the upside and continue in
this up Trend but as you can see we have
our valid double bottom trade scenario
that you've learned throughout this
whole video I don't need to go over that
again but what I do want to share with
you is two other technical factors that
can dramatically increase the accuracy
of double bottom and double top trades
the first is something I talk about all
too often and that is valuable levels of
structure or major levels of structure
that have been tested multiple times so
this is the way I personally like to
trade these I don't like to trade them
in the middle of nowhere but I love
trading these patterns in the way you've
learned in this video If price is
already at a major level of structure
and my Perfect Trading scenario is when
I can add one other technical factor to
this technical Factor along with the
double bottom trading strategy and chart
pattern you've already learned and that
other technical factor is in fact the
RSI indicator if I see the RSI go
oversold or even better get what is
called Divergence quick lesson on
Divergence if price is making
equal or lower lows while in fact the
RSI indicator is making higher lows that
is called RSI Divergence so if I can get
the double bottom chart pattern and
strategy you've learned throughout the
video inside of a major level of
structure with RSI Divergence that is my
absolutely perfect scenario for this
entire trading strategy and for anytime
I want to trade double bottoms and
double tops and as you can see again I
wanted to show you a couple of live
trades so you can see that all this was
was not just in hindsight I use this on
a daily basis in my trading and I have
for the past eight years one other trade
we're going to take a look at is the
Euro Swiss and this is a trade I'm still
in that hasn't even hit our first
targets yet so this trade if we look
left let's go ahead and start with the
first condition a level of structure
that's been tested multiple times so
here on the Euros Swiss we absolutely
have that we have this level where price
has acted as support support resistance
resistance support support
resistance definitely been tested
multiple times price then if I zoom in
to make this easier to see comes down
creates a double bottom while inside of
this Zone meeting all the criteria for
our double bottom we then break above
our neckline which is where my entry was
we pushed up almost got to a 1.4 but not
quite and my actual exit for this trade
is up here close to our next level of
resistance now stick around because
again right after this I'm going to be
talking you through the number one
problem that's keep keeping you from
being profitable and how to fix it but
let's discuss these two technical
factors one more time we have the full
double bottom strategy you've learned
throughout the entire video but when
adding these two technical factors it
dramatically increases the accuracy of
these patterns what two technical
factors is that that would be major
levels of structure that have been
tested multiple times like we see here
on the Euro Swiss and what was the other
one it's going to be RS I Divergence as
you see if we look down here we have a
low on the RSI we have an equal low on
price while the RSI is in fact heading
higher giving us RSI Divergence and
giving us all the Confluence we need to
have this as an A+ trading setup using
the double bottom strategy you've
learned throughout this video now
although you know a full accurate
trading strategy from what you've
learned so far in this video it will
mean absolutely nothing if you cannot
fix the mistake that h hinders so many
Traders from becoming consistently
profitable this mistake is very simple
but is detrimental if you continue to
make it throughout your trading career
and will cause you to blow your entire
account and eventually completely give
up on trading what is this mistake it is
a lack of patience let me explain by
first telling you the top four signs
that you have a lack of patience in your
own trading side number one you are
constantly taking trades that do not fit
in with your trading plan because you're
not patient enough to wait for the
perfect trading opportunity side effect
number two you're constantly switching
between different strategies because you
don't have the patience to allow one
strategy to play out over a large enough
sample size to let that edge go to work
side effect number three you're risking
too much money on each trade trying to
get rich quick because you're not
patient enough to use proper risk
management and side effect number four
you're taking off targets early every
single time even though you had an
initial Target you're taking the Target
off before it gets there because you're
not patient enough to let that trade
play out if you are suffering from any
of those then it's vital that you watch
the rest of this video so here's how we
fix that I've been trading for over a
decade I've suffered with my own lack of
patience throughout that time I've also
been teaching Traders around the world
for over six years so I've seen the
detrimental effects the lack of patients
can do to others as well and often times
s Traders will ask me through email or
whether it be email or FaceTime how can
I become more patient here's the answer
to that no one can teach you how to be
patient patience comes down to your
willingness to do what you know is right
and to avoid doing what you know is
wrong here's what I mean by that you
already know that you shouldn't be
trading outside of your trading plan but
you're having a hard time sitting on
your hands and not placing trades
because you're too impatient to do so
that has nothing to do with something I
can teach you you already know that's
the wrong decision to make what's
happening is you're not letting you're
not having enough willpower to actually
control the decision-making process
you're letting greed and that Rush of
gambling take control of you and that is
going to cause you to be impatient that
feeling if you cannot control it will be
the demise of your trading account
that's the first
thing another thing is I can tell you
things that can inspire you to be
patient but inspiration does not last
that long have you ever been inspired to
lose weight or inspired to gain muscle
and get big if you have then you know
that that inspiration might last a week
or two what changes your body literally
it's not you watching videos on YouTube
about working out watching videos on
YouTube about losing weight thinking
about working out thinking about losing
weight it's the actions and habits that
you do that you actually do those are
the things that will change your body
and in terms of becoming a more patient
traitor it's the actions and habits you
take it's not asking your Mentor how to
be more patient asking questions is it
going to do it it's not having the idea
that you want to be more patient it's
right at the point when you're about to
make a decision that you know is not the
right decision when you're about to take
targets off early it's right before you
make that decision and click that button
thinking are these the ACT and habits of
a patient and professional
Trader if they are not then do not do
them obviously switching strategies
every week is not the actions of a
patient and a professional Trader you
know that but you lack the willpower to
act accordingly and not switch
strategies that is because of greed and
fear and those are two things that you
must learn how to control no one can
teach you how to control greed and fear
it's up to you you to adopt the habits
of someone that has discipline to adopt
the habits of someone who is patient and
who is a professional Trader before
you're ever going to be able to achieve
that for
yourself so those are the ways around
and the best lessons and the best
inspiration that I can give you on being
patient is one inspiration is only going
to last so long it's up to you to take
the actions that you know a patient and
professional Trader would take that's
that's going to be something that you
will have to control no one else can do
that for you so keep that in mind but
here is where I'm going to hit you with
the toughest Love of All if you try to
do that for six months after watching
this video you try your best to be
patient to not switch strategies to not
risk too much each trade you try your
best to stick to a trading plan and you
just literally cannot do it something in
you is forcing you to place trades
outside of your your plan to risk more
than you know you should because you
want to get rich fast if that is the
case
then it's very likely that you are
addicted to the rush of gambling and
trading in financial markets is going to
be very very tough for you and it's time
at that point after you have attempted
consciously tried to become more patient
for 6 months and it still does not work
for you it's at that point that I would
personally suggest you take a large step
back and fix that problem of being
addicted to the rush of gambling before
continuing to try to create a career out
of trading and I say that with love
because if you don't fix that Rush that
addiction to the rush of gambling you're
never going to be a profitable Trader
and I'm sorry to say you're going to end
up blowing your account or completely
giving up on trading altogether after a
series of terrible losses and of course
I do not want to see you lose your hard
hard earned money sorry to end on such a
dark note but sometimes tough love is
necessary if you really want to help
someone and I am in no way shape or form
accusing any of you of being addicted to
gambling all I'm saying is that if you
truly consciously attempt to fix all
these mistakes for a six-month period
and you can't do so because of greed you
do need to take a step back and ensure
that it's not an addiction to gambling
that you have but with that being said I
do hope you enjoyed today's video hope
you learned something from it if you did
click that like button for me comment if
you made it to the end subscribe if you
are new be sure to check out the TTC
forx University we still have a little
bit of space left in that course it's
essentially our version of a mentorship
program here at CTC it'll be the top
Link in the description or you go to
www.tcf university.com I wish you all
the best of luck in your future trades
and I'll talk to you in the next video
see you soon